A Guide to the Warwick County (Va.) Records, 1650-1840
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Warwick County (Va.) Records, 1650-1840
The Library of Virginia
0007417216
1 box.
Newport News (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer under the accession numbers 18655, 20321, 21071, 21369, 21708, 22028, 22057, 22641, 22642, 24853, 24867, 25129, 28694, 31286, and 31287.
The will of Henry Cary, 1716, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer from the Monticello Association Archives under the accession number 50827.
Historical Information
Warwick County was named either for Robert Rich, earl of Warwick, a prominent member of the London Company, or for the county of Warwick in England. The county was originally called Warwick River and was one of the original shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634. The shorter name was adopted in 1643. Warwick County became extinct in 1952, when it became the city of Warwick. The new city was consolidated with the city of Newport News in 1958 and took the latter's name. Denbigh was the county seat.
County court records were destroyed at several times with most destruction occurring during the Civil War. The clerk's office was burned on 15 December 1864. County court minute books and loose records from 1787 to 1819 were destroyed by the fire. Additional records were burned in Richmond on 3 April 1865, where they had been moved for safekeeping during the Civil War.
A portion of the records in the collection were returned to Warwick County in 1914. E. Russell Jones returned Warwick County records found among the effects of a deceased relative who served in the Civil War. James P. Williams returned Warwick County records he received from a friend named Edward G. Wood whose grandfather was a collector of relics.
Scope and Content
Warwick County (Va.) Records, 1650-1840, include county court orders, county claims, order book, docket book, pages from order books, judgments, chancery cause, deeds, justice of the peace commission, and fiduciary records. Information found in order book and pages from order books include deeds, wills, estate inventories, and summary of suits heard in county court.
The collection includes correspondence dated 1914 between the clerk of Warwick County and two individuals from Philadelphia, PA regarding the return of some of the records found in this collection to Warwick County.
Conservation for a portion of the Warwick County Records including the will of Henry Cary, 1716, was funded through a donation made by John C.R. Taylor III.
Conservation for a portion of the Warwick County Records was funded through a donation made by the Jamestowne Chapter of the Colonial Daughters of the 17th Century.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
For more information and a listing of lost records localities see Lost Records research note.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Newport News (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records -- Virginia -- Warwick County.
Geographical Names:
Warwick County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records -- Virginia -- Newport News.
Added Entry - Corporate Name:
Warwick County (Va.) County Court.
Contents list
- Pages from Order Book, 1650-1651
- Division of real and personal property, 1656-1686:
  Primarily records division of cattle and horses among orphans. Also includes references to slaves.
- Cattle account, 1657
- Indenture signed by Henry Dawson and Brian Canaday, 1662
- Page from Order Book, 1663
- Obligation, 1668
- Assignment of bond, 1678
- Page from Order Book, 1680
- Pages from Order Book, 1685:
  Includes estate inventories and will.
- Page from Order Book, 1687-1688
- Page from Order Book, 1688
- Capias, Wills vs. Lisny 1689
- Page from Order Book, 1690/91
- Page from Court of Claims Order Book, 1691:
  Includes payment of claims for recovering runaway indentured servants and Native American servants.
- Pages from Deeds, etc., Order Book, 1695-1697:
  Records deeds, wills, and estate inventories.
- Appointment of Mary Kingston as executrix of Nicholas Kingston, 1697
- Order Book, 1697-1698:
  Pages 211-216 and 225-230
- Pages from Order Book, 1701
- Miscellaneous court records, 1701-1728
- Executor's bond, 1703
- Pages from Order Book, 1705
  Pages 457-458
- Page from Order Book, 1705
  Pages 461-464
- Will of James Brown, 1707
- Judgments and chancery cause, 1707, 1728, 1730
  Capias - James Bates vs Edward Loftis, 1707
  Declaration - Robert Rullison and Dorothy Price vs. Richard Hyde, 1728
  Chancery Cause - Elizabeth Cary vs Thomas Harwood, 1730
- Order Book, 1713-1714
- Release Deed, 1715
- Will of Henry Cary, 1716
- Writ, Simson vs. Hubbard 1725
- Petition and summons, Hobday, etc. vs. Noblin 1769
- Judgment - Exr. of William Haynes vs. John Wills, Jr., 1770
- Will of Susannah Godwin, 1782
- Casa: John Perry vs James Crandol, 1785
- Capias, McKintosh, etc. vs. Gray, etc. 1787
- Judgment, McKintosh, etc. vs. Gray, etc. 1788
- Deed - Servant Ballard to Isaac Avery, 1792
- Deed and plat - William Aylett to Richard Cary, 1798
- Deed - Richard Cary and wife to William Aylett, 1798
- Capias: Administrator of Thomas Mallicote vs Peter Houghton, 1799
- Chancery subpoena, Brown, etc. vs. Dunn and wife, 1801
- Deed, Allen and wife to Gambol 1804
- Docket Book, 1813-1818
- Jail report, 1825 September
- Fifa, Sheild, assignee vs. Harwood, etc. 1837
- Fifa, Smith, assignee vs. Harwood, etc. 1837
- Fifa, Judith Blake for Henry Burton vs John Dixon and Mann Page(originated in Gloucester County), 1827
- Jail report, undated
- Justice of the Peace Commission 1840